Lycopene is the
phytonutrient
that gives tomatoes
their bright red color.
It’s among the most potent
of carotenoid antioxidants,
so what happened
when researchers
pitted lycopene and
whole tomatoes
against prostate cancer?
Check it out.
"Lycopene Supplements vs. Prostate Cancer &
Tomato Sauce vs. Prostate Cancer"
Back in the '80s, the Adventist Health Study
found strong protective relationships
against prostate cancer with
increasing consumption
of legumes, citrus, dried
fruit, nuts, and tomatoes.
In the '90s, a Harvard study
focused attention on tomatoes,
which appeared to be
especially beneficial.
They suspected it might be the red
pigment in tomatoes called lycopene,
which has greater antioxidant power
than some of the other pigments,
like the orange beta-carotene
pigment in carrots and cantaloupes.
And lycopene dramatically kills off
prostate cancer cells in a petri dish,
even way down at the
levels one would expect
in one's blood stream after
just eating some tomatoes.
So of course the Heinz
ketchup company,
along with manufacturers
of lycopene supplements,
petitioned the FDA to allow them to
print health claims on their products.
They were essentially denied, saying
that the evidence was very limited
and preliminary, with no endorsement
allowed for ketchup or supplements.
By that time, further population studies
had cast doubt on the lycopene theory.
Consumers of high dietary
intakes of lycopene
didn't seem to have lower
cancer rates after all.
But who has high dietary
intakes of lycopene?
Those that eat the most pizza;
so maybe it's no surprise
there are mixed results.
What we need is to put
lycopene to the test.
It started with a case study.
A 62-year old man with terminal
prostate cancer, failed surgery,
failed chemotherapy, metastases
all over, spread to the bone.
And so he was sent
to hospice to die.
So he took it upon himself to initiate
phytotherapy, plant-based therapy,
taking the amount of lycopene found
in a quarter cup of tomato sauce
or a tablespoon of
tomato paste every day.
His PSA, a measure of tumor
bulk, started out as 365,
but dropped to 140 the next
month, and then down to 8.
His metastases started disappearing,
and as of his last follow-up
appeared to be living
happily ever after.
But when given in higher dose pill
form, lycopene didn't seem to work.
A 2013 review of all such
lycopene supplement trials
failed to support
the initial optimism.
In fact, they were just happy
that the lycopene pills
didn't end up causing more cancer,
like beta-carotene pills did.
But then came 2014.
Researchers in Italy had been giving
the largest doses they could
of lycopene, selenium, and
isolated green tea compounds
to men with precancerous
prostate lesions,
hoping they could prevent
full-blown cancer.
But in 2014, the expanded results
of a similar trial were published
in which selenium and vitamin E
supplements resulted in more cancer.
Yikes!
So these researchers
stopped their trial
and broke the code to
un-blind the results.
And indeed, those taking high doses
of lycopene, green tea catechins,
and selenium appeared to get more cancer
than those who just got sugar pills.
"The potential implications are dramatic,"
said the lead researcher,
"given the current massive
worldwide use of such compounds
as alleged preventive supplementations
in prostate and other cancers."
What went wrong?
Well, after the beta-
carotene pill debacle,
researchers measured
cellular damage at different
natural and unnatural
doses of beta-carotene.
At dietary doses, beta-carotene
suppressed cellular damage,
but at higher supplemental doses,
it not only appeared to stop
working, but caused more damage.
And the same with lycopene.
Both lycopene and beta-
carotene afforded protection
against DNA damage at the
kinds of levels one might see
in people eating lots of
tomatoes or sweet potatoes,
levels comparable with those
seen in the blood of individuals
who consume a carotenoid-
rich healthy diet.
However, at the kind of blood
concentrations that one might get
taking pills, the ability
to protect the cell against
such free radical damage
was rapidly lost.
And indeed, the presence of high
levels of beta-carotene and lycopene
may actually serve to increase
the extent of DNA damage.
So no wonder high dose
lycopene pills didn't work.
Phytochemicals may be
guardians of our health,
but the safety of consuming
concentrated extracts is unknown.
The protective benefits of
a phytochemical-rich diet
are best obtained by
whole plant foods.
The food industry has
different ideas, though.
Soon there may be phytochemical-
fortified bacon, martinis, and ice cream,
says this article in the
Journal of Food Technology.
If they can find just the right
mix of plant compounds,
they hope to reconstruct foods that
once contributed to illness and disease
to offer significant
health benefits.
"Occasionally...positive
things happen in the field
of cancer prevention science
to popular, good-tasting foods."
Yes, broccoli family
vegetables are wonderful,
but may be a hard food
for the public to swallow.
By contrast, who doesn't
like tomatoes?
But studies using high dose
supplements of lycopene,
the antioxidant red pigment
in tomatoes thought to be
the active anti-cancer ingredient,
failed over and over again
to prevent or treat cancer,
and may even end
up promoting it,
since at the high levels one
can get with supplements,
lycopene may actually
act as a pro-oxidant.
But lycopene
doesn't appear
to be effective at
lower doses either.
There is a strong
protective correlation
between the intake of actual
whole fruit and vegetables
and the incidence
of certain cancers,
but when we supplement
with only a single compound
isolated in pill form,
we may upset
the healthy natural
balance of antioxidants.
It does seem to be
quite the human hubris
to think we can reproduce
the beneficial effects
of consuming entire
fruits and vegetables
by giving supplements
of a single phytochemical,
which would normally interact
with thousands of other compounds
in the natural matrix
Mother Nature intended.
In addition to lycopene,
other carotenoids in tomatoes
include beta-carotene,
gamma-carotene, zeta-carotene,
phytofluene, and phytoene,
all of which are known
to accumulate in
human prostate tissue.
And there are also numerous
non-carotenoid compounds
in tomatoes that may
have anti-cancer activity,
not to mention all the compounds
we have yet to even characterize.
But it's not about finding
the one magic bullet;
the anti-cancer effects
of carotenoids
and other phytonutrients may
reside in their combined activity.
For example, at
low concentrations
of the tomato compounds
phytoene, phytofluene,
and lycopene found in most
people who eat normal amounts
of tomatoes, there's
very little effect
on cancer cell growth
in vitro, used separately,
but combine them
all together
and a non-effective dose
plus a non-effective dose
becomes effective somehow,
significantly suppressing
prostate cancer cell growth.
And the same synergy
can be seen across foods.
Curcumin, the yellow pigment
in turmeric and curry powder,
tomato extracts, and the vitamin E
found in nuts and seeds
do little to inhibit
pro-growth signaling
of prostate cancer cells—
less than 10%.
But all three together suppresses
growth signaling like 70%.
The whole is greater
than the sum of its parts.
So how about instead of giving
cancer patients lycopene pills,
we give them some
tomato sauce?
Thirty-two patients with
localized prostate cancer
were given three quarters of a cup
of canned tomato sauce every day
for three weeks before their
scheduled radical prostatectomy.
In their bloodstream, PSA
levels dropped by 17.5%.
PSA, prostate-specific antigen,
is a protein produced
by prostate gland cells,
and elevated blood levels
are routinely used
to monitor the success
of cancer treatment.
It was surprising to find
that in just 3 weeks,
a tomato sauce-based dietary
intervention could decrease
PSA concentrations in
men with prostate cancer.
Also, free radical
damage of the DNA
in their white blood
cells dropped by 21%.
Imagine how antioxidant poor their
diet must have been beforehand,
if less than a cup of tomato
sauce a day could reduce
DNA damage by
more than a fifth.
OK, but what did they
find in their prostates?
Human prostate tissue is thought
to be particularly vulnerable
to oxidative DNA damage
by free radicals,
which are thought
to play a critical role
in all stages of
cancer formation.
This may be for a
number of reasons,
including fewer
DNA repair enzymes.
Well, the researchers had
tissue samples taken
before the tomato sauce from
biopsies, and tissue samples
from the surgery after the
three weeks of tomato sauce,
and resected tissues from tomato
sauce-supplemented patients
had 28% less free radical
damage than expected.
Here's the DNA damage in the
prostate before the tomato sauce,
and here's after,
just 20 days of sauce.
And what's interesting is
that there was no association
between the level of
lycopene in the prostate
and the protective effects.
Tomatoes contain a
whole bunch of things,
some of which may be even
more powerful than lycopene.
Regardless, in contrast to the
lycopene supplements alone,
the whole food intervention
seemed to help.
To see if lycopene
plays any role at all,
one would have to test
a lycopene-free tomato—
in other words,
a yellow tomato.
So what if you compared red
tomatoes to yellow tomatoes,
which have all the non-lycopene
tomato compounds,
to straight lycopene in a pill.
So they fed people red tomato
paste, yellow tomato paste,
lycopene pills, or placebo pills,
and then dripped their blood
on prostate cancer cells
growing in a petri dish.
Compared to those not eating
anything, the red tomato serum,
the blood from those
who ate red tomato paste
significantly decreased
the prostate cancer cell's
expression of a growth-promoting
gene called cyclin D1.
This downregulation of the gene
by the red tomato consumption
may contribute to lower
prostate cancer risk
by limiting cell proliferation.
The red tomato seemed to
work better than the yellow,
so maybe the lycopene
helped, but not in pill form.
This gene was not regulated
by the lycopene pill serum,
indicating that maybe
it's something else.
And lycopene alone
significantly upregulated
procarcinogenic genes.
Therefore, it can be stated
that tomato consumption
may be preferable.
So what's the best way?
A spouse wrote in to the editor
of the Harvard Men's Health Watch
saying his or her husband wants
to have pizza for his prostate,
to which the doctor replied, fine,
but how about cheese-free pizza
with broccoli instead
of pepperoni,
or he can just drink
some tomato juice.